<resources>
  <string name="app_name">Konstellations</string>
  <string name="shortcut_disabled_message">Shortcut Disabled</string>
  <!-- Long label should be <= 25 characters-->
  <string name="shortcut_long_label">Random Constellation</string>
  <!-- Short label should be <= 10 characters-->
  <string name="shortcut_short_label">Random</string>

  <string name="aquarius">Aquarius</string>
  <string name="aquila">Aquila, the Eagle</string>
  <string name="aries">Aries, the Ram</string>
  <string name="auriga">Auriga, the Charioteer</string>
  <string name="bootes">Boötes, the Herdsman</string>
  <string name="cancer">Cancer, the Crab</string>
  <string name="canis_major">Canis Major, the Great Dog</string>
  <string name="capricornus">Capricornus, the Sea-Goat</string>
  <string name="cassiopeia">Cassiopeia, the Queen</string>
  <string name="cygnus">Cygnus, the Swan</string>
  <string name="gemini">Gemini, the Twins</string>
  <string name="leo">Leo, the Lion</string>
  <string name="libra">Libra, the Scales</string>
  <string name="lyra">Lyra, the Harp</string>
  <string name="orion">Orion, the Hunter</string>
  <string name="pegasus">Pegasus, the Flying Horse</string>
  <string name="perseus">Perseus, the Hero</string>
  <string name="pisces">Pisces, the Fish</string>
  <string name="sagittarius">Sagittarius, the Archer</string>
  <string name="scorpius">Scorpius, the Scorpion</string>
  <string name="taurus">Taurus, the Bull</string>
  <string name="ursa_major">Ursa Major, the Great Bear</string>
  <string name="virgo">Virgo</string>

  <string name="aquila_short_name">Aquila</string>
  <string name="aries_short_name">Aries</string>
  <string name="auriga_short_name">Auriga</string>
  <string name="bootes_short_name">Boötes</string>
  <string name="cancer_short_name">Cancer</string>
  <string name="canis_major_short_name">Canis Major</string>
  <string name="capricornus_short_name">Capricornus</string>
  <string name="cassiopeia_short_name">Cassiopeia</string>
  <string name="cygnus_short_name">Cygnus</string>
  <string name="gemini_short_name">Gemini</string>
  <string name="leo_short_name">Leo</string>
  <string name="libra_short_name">Libra</string>
  <string name="lyra_short_name">Lyra</string>
  <string name="orion_short_name">Orion</string>
  <string name="pegasus_short_name">Pegasus</string>
  <string name="perseus_short_name">Perseus</string>
  <string name="pisces_short_name">Pisces</string>
  <string name="sagittarius_short_name">Sagittarius</string>
  <string name="scorpius_short_name">Scorpius</string>
  <string name="taurus_short_name">Taurus</string>
  <string name="ursa_major_short_name">Ursa Major</string>

  <string name="aquarius_desc">Thanks to its position in the zodiac, not to mention a hit Broadway song, Aquarius, the water bearer, is one of the most famous constellations. But few people have actually seen it because it\'s so faint. It is home to the summer Delta Aquarid meteor shower, which like the constellation itself is fairly thin and sparse.\n\nSeveral of the stars of Aquarius have names that signify luck or good fortune. The most prominent examples are the constellation\'s two brightest stars, Sadalmelik and Sadalsuud. The names are from ancient Arabic, and mean "lucky one of the king" and "luckiest of the lucky." The names may refer to the stars\' positions. When the constellations were named, the Sun passed through this region of the sky in early spring, when the long nights of winter had passed and the new season brought life-giving rains. Aquarius is one of several \"watery\" constellations in that part of the sky.\n\nThe constellation is home to the globular cluster M2. It is 38,000 light-years from Earth, but is bright enough to see through binoculars because it consists of about 100,000 stars packed into a dense ball just a few light-years in diameter.\n\nThe cluster is one of the oldest objects in the galaxy, so all of its bright, heavy stars have long since expired. The brightest stars in M2 today are yellow and orange giants — stars that were once like the Sun, but that expanded and brightened as they consumed the nuclear fuel in their cores. M2 doesn\'t belong to the Milky Way galaxy’s flat disk. In fact, the disk didn’t even exist when M2 was born. Instead, M2 is part of the galaxy’s halo — a shell of stars that surrounds the disk.\n\nAnother of Aquarius\' wonders is an obscure star system known as Gliese 876. The star itself is a red dwarf, which is the smallest, faintest class of stars. Gliese 876 is only a third as massive as the Sun, and looks about a thousandth as bright. So even though it is just 15 light-years away, it is far too faint to see without a telescope.\n\nThe system contains at least four planets, including one that may be one of the most Earth-like worlds yet discovered. From a tiny \"wobble\" in the star\'s light caused by the planet\'s gravitational pull, along with other evidence, astronomers calculate that the planet probably is about twice as big as Earth and a few times more massive. Like Earth, it\'s probably a rocky world. And its gravity is strong enough to retain any atmosphere it was born with. The planet isn\'t a likely home for life, though, because it\'s so close to Gliese 876 that surface temperatures are hundreds of degrees. So if anything lives on the planet, it would have to be quite different from life on Earth.</string>
  <string name="aquila_desc">Aquila glides on outstretched wings through the glowing band of the Milky Way. Look for it high in the south in late summer.\n\nThe brightest star in Aquila is Altair, \"the eagle,\" a white star that is about 17 light-years from Earth. Altair is the southern point of a pattern of three bright stars called the Summer Triangle. (Deneb, in the constellation Cygnus, forms the triangle\'s northeastern point. Vega, in Lyra, the harp, is in the northwest. Altair is nice and bright and easy to find right up to the beginning of winter.)\n\nAltair is about twice as massive as the Sun, so it will live only about two billion years versus the Sun\'s 10 billion. Despite its size, Altair appears to turn on its axis once every 10 hours, compared to about four weeks for the Sun. One of the effects of Altair\'s high-speed rotation is that its gas is forced outward at the equator, giving the star a flattened appearance — it is about 14 percent wider through the equator than through the poles. If Altair spun about twice as fast as it does now it would fly apart.\n\nAquila\'s two \"tail\" stars are Zeta and Epsilon Aquilae. Together, they also have an older Arabic name: Deneb al Okab, \"the eagle\'s tail.\" The northern star in the tail is actually a system of three or more stars. Only one of them is bright enough to see with the unaided eye. It\'s a type of star known as a red giant. That means it\'s in the final stages of life. Its core is getting hotter and denser, while its outer layers are puffing out and getting cooler. That\'s the same process that awaits the Sun in several billion years. The southern star is a multiple-star system, too. Its brightest star is fairly early in life. It\'s bigger, heavier, and hotter than the Sun, and it spins close to 200 times faster than the Sun, so like Aquila it bulges out at the equator, so it looks like a squashed beachball.\n\nThe Pioneer 11 spacecraft, which was launched in 1973, is heading toward one of the eagle\'s stars, Lambda Aquilae, which is 125 light-years away. Pioneer will pass the star in about four million years. Although the spacecraft has already expired, it carries a message from home: a small plaque with information about the craft and its makers — a greeting to the galaxy from the people who made Pioneer 11.</string>
  <string name="aries_desc">Aries, the ram, is a faint pattern marked by only a couple of fairly bright stars: Hamal, its brightest, and Sheratan, its second-brightest.\n\nAries is famous not because of its brilliance, though, but because of its location: It is one of the 12 constellations of the zodiac. These constellations straddle the Sun\'s path across the sky, known as the ecliptic. In ancient times, that gave these regions of the sky extra significance.\n\nAries was the most significant of all. At the time the constellations were named, the Sun appeared against the stars of Aries at the vernal equinox, which is the first day of spring in the northern hemisphere. With the earth awakening from its winter slumber, the equinox was a time of celebration. And it usually marked the beginning of a new year.\n\nToday, the Sun\'s location at the equinox is still known as the \"first point of Aries,\" even though the Sun is in Pisces. The change is caused by a slow wobble in Earth\'s axis. The Sun will return to Aries — and the ram will regain his status as the leader of the zodiacal flock — when we complete one full wobble in about 22,000 years.\n\nHamal, the constellation\'s brightest star, is classified as an orange giant. That means it is much larger and brighter than the Sun — bright enough to see even though it is more than 65 light-years away.\n\nGiant stars have burned through the original hydrogen fuel in their cores. The cores basically \"retool\" to process other elements: They shrink and get hotter. In response, the outer layers puff outward. A giant can expand from about the size of the Sun, which is less than a million miles in diameter, to tens of millions of miles.\n\nOne of the ram\'s most important stars is too faint to see without a telescope. Yet half a century ago, it played a key role in a revolutionary discovery: Most of the chemical elements on Earth — and in our bodies — were forged in the stars.\n\nFor a long time, scientists didn\'t know where the oxygen, silicon, iron, and other heavy elements that make up Earth came from. A faint star in Aries, HD 19445, along with a star in Libra, helped point the way.\n\nIn 1951, astronomers reported that these two stars had much less iron and calcium than the Sun. It was a shocking report, because most astronomers thought that nearly all stars had the same composition. Around this time, though, they realized that the two iron-deficient stars were very old, so they had formed in the galaxy\'s earliest years. Since the stars had little iron, it meant that the young galaxy itself had little iron. The galaxy has grown more iron-rich over time, though, as stars created iron and spewed it into space. So younger stars like the Sun have higher concentrations of iron and other heavy elements than older stars.\n\nThe implication of this discovery was simple but profound: The stars created the iron in our blood, the calcium in our bones, and the oxygen we breathe.</string>
  <string name="auriga_desc">Auriga, the celestial charioteer, has neither chariot nor horse. Instead, he\'s drawn as a man holding the reins in his right hand, with a goat on his left shoulder — the star Capella — and two baby goats in his left arm. Look for him cruising high across the southern evening sky in January and February.\n\nThe constellation has an uncertain origin. It might represent Neptune rising from the sea in a chariot. Or it might honor a legendary king of Athens; according to this tale, he invented a chariot that was drawn by four horses.\n\nCapella is one of the few bright stars that is yellow, like our Sun. The similar color indicates that they have roughly the same surface temperature. But the light from Capella actually comes from two separate stars. Both are yellow, and both lie about 43 light-years from Earth. Each star emits dozens of times more light than the Sun.\n\nIts brightness and position in the night sky have made Capella an important star in many cultures. An example is the ancient Mexican city of Monte Alban, where a temple was dedicated to astronomical observations. Some of its structures align with the point on the horizon where Capella made its first dawn appearance. That appearance happened on one of the two days of the year when the Sun passed directly overhead. So Capella might have acted like a warning flag, alerting the city\'s leaders that the time for the year\'s most important ceremonies was at hand.</string>
  <string name="bootes_desc">The brightest stars of Boötes form a cone shape, with brilliant yellow-orange Arcturus at the base of the cone. The name Boötes comes from a Sumerian word that means \"Man Who Drove the Great Cart.\" The \"Great Cart\" was the Big Dipper. Boötes trails the Big Dipper as it wheels around the North Star.\n\nArcturus, the fourth-brightest star in Earth\'s night sky, is about 20 times larger than the Sun, and it produces about a hundred times as much energy. But Arcturus is nearing the end of its life. In astronomical parlance, Arcturus has moved off the main sequence and entered the \"giant\" phase of its life. At a distance of about 35 light-years, it\'s closer to us than any other stellar giant.\n\nAstronomers used light from Arcturus to help trip a switch that opened the 1933 World\'s Fair in Chicago.</string>
  <string name="cancer_desc">Although it is one of the constellations of the zodiac, Cancer plays a relatively small role in both sky and skylore.\n\nIt is a small constellation of faint stars, so it is difficult to find in the sky.\n\nIn mythology, it forms part of the story of Hercules. According to one version of the tale, while Hercules was tackling the multi-headed monster Hydra, the goddess Hera sent a giant crab to distract the strongman. Unfortunately for the big crustacean, though, it wasn\'t much of a challenge. Hercules crushed it, then quickly returned to his monster killing. Hera placed the remains of the crab in the sky, but gave it only faint stars because of its failure.\n\nThe constellation\'s most prominent feature is the star cluster M44, the Beehive Cluster. It is about 600 light-years away and more than 10 light-years wide. To the unaided eye it looks like a small, fuzzy patch of light — like a tiny cloud floating through the stars. But telescopes reveal that the cloud is actually a cluster of hundreds of individual stars.\n\nThe stars of the Beehive are all members of a big family. They all formed at the same time, from the same cloud of gas and dust. The most recent estimates put their age at around 600 million to 700 million years, which makes them four billion years younger than the Sun.\n\nAstronomers deduce M44\'s age by determining the types of stars it contains and the types it does not. Missing from the cluster are the hottest, brightest, and most massive classes of stars. Such stars burn through their nuclear fuel in a hurry, so they disappear in tens or hundreds of millions of years, placing a lower limit on the cluster\'s age.\n\nMost of the cluster\'s current members are the faint cosmic embers known as red dwarfs, while about a third are somewhat like the Sun. Only a handful of stars are much brighter and more massive than the Sun, and these will burn out fairly soon on the astronomical time scale.\n\nA much older cluster also lurks with Cancer\'s borders: M67. It is similar to M44 except for its age, which is about the same as the age of the Sun. Most clusters don\'t survive more than a few trips around the center of the galaxy because the gravity of other stars and giant clouds of gas and dust pull them apart. Yet M67 has survived for four or five billion years. That\'s because it resides in the outer part of the galaxy, where there are fewer stars and gas clouds to disturb it.\n\nOne other resident of note is the planetary system 55 Cancri. It consists of five known planets, with perhaps several more awaiting discovery.\n\nThe system is about 40 light-years away, and is faintly visible to the unaided eye, although you need help to find it. It consists of two wide-spaced stars, one of which is similar to the Sun, and which hosts the planets. The innermost of its planets is a \"super Earth,\" which means it\'s only a few times heavier than our world — one of the lightest-weight planets yet discovered. The other planets are much bigger and heavier. None of the planets is in the star\'s habitable zone, which is the distance from the star at which liquid water could exist on the surface. Since water is a necessary ingredient for life as we know it, none of the planets is considered a likely abode for life.</string>
  <string name="canis_major_desc">Canis Major loyally follows its mythical master, Orion, across the southern skies of winter.\n\nThe brightest star in Canis Major also is the brightest in the entire night sky — brilliant Sirius, which is just 8.6 light-years away. That\'s only twice as far as our closest stellar neighbor. Because it is the brightest star of the Great Dog, Sirius is known as the Dog Star. Its first appearance in the dawn sky in August heralds the \"dog days\" of summer.\n\nSirius is actually a double star. The star that we see as Sirius is about 20 times brighter than the Sun. It is also hotter and more massive than the Sun. Its companion is known as Sirius B, and is nicknamed The Pup. It is a white dwarf — the hot, dense core of a star that was once like Sirius itself. At the end of its life, the star blew its outer layers into space, leaving only the core. Sirius B is as massive as the Sun but less than one percent as bright. It shines simply because it\'s still hot.\n\nCanis Major\'s second-brightest star is Adhara. It is well below Sirius, in one of the dog\'s legs. It is about 425 light-years away. It emits about a thousand times more visible light than Sirius does, so if it were moved to the same distance as Sirius, it would look about 200 times brighter than Sirius does. Because the surface of Adhara is extremely hot, the star emits more ultraviolet energy than visible light. If our eyes were tuned to the ultraviolet, Adhara would outshine every other star in the night sky.\n\nOne interesting sight in Canis Major is a star cluster known as M41, which is about 2,300 light-years away. It\'s visible to the unaided eye as a faint smudge of light below Sirius. Binoculars or a small telescope reveal a swarm of several dozen stars.</string>
  <string name="capricornus_desc">Capricornus, the sea goat, bounds low across the southern sky in late summer and fall. Like all the constellations of the zodiac, Capricornus has as many mythological tales as it has stars. Capricornus gets its name from a Greek myth that says the god Pan was transformed into a half-goat, half-fish when he dived into the Nile River to escape the giant Typhon.\n\nCapricornus looks like a large triangle of fairly bright stars. The brightest stars are side-by-side at the triangle\'s western tip. Farthest west is Giedi — the goat. Binoculars reveal that this is really two stars. Although the stars appear near each other, they\'re really separated by a thousand light-years. The closer of the two is about 115 light-years from Earth, while the other is 10 times farther. Just southeast of Giedi is Dabih, the slaughterer — a name that refers to sacrifices made by ancient Arabs when Capricornus rose at the same time as the Sun. It, too, consists of more than one star.</string>
  <string name="cassiopeia_desc">The mythological queen Cassiopeia floats overhead in fall and winter.\n\nThe best time to see her is in late fall, when she stands high in the northeastern sky during the evening hours. Cassiopeia looks like a flattened \"W\" against the frothy background of our home galaxy, the Milky Way.\n\nGamma Cassiopeia is the star at the middle of the W. If you add up all of its energy — not just the light that is visible to the eye — it shines about 40,000 times brighter than the Sun. That\'s because Gamma Cas is about 15 times as massive as the Sun and hundreds of times wider. Such a monster produces a lot of energy through the nuclear reactions in its core. That energy works its way to the surface and shines into space as visible light, ultraviolet, and other forms of electromagnetic energy. Eventually, the star will no longer be able to produce energy in its core, causing the core to collapse and its outer layers to explode as a supernova. For a few days or weeks, it will outshine everything in the night sky except the Moon.\n\nAnother of the constellation\'s stars, Rho Cassiopeia, is also destined to explode as a supernova. It is about 10,000 light-years away, making it one of the most distant stars that is visible to the unaided eye.\n\nRho Cas, which is to the right of Cassiopeia\'s W, is far bigger and more massive than the Sun and at least a half-million times brighter. It may be just about as bright as a star can get without blowing itself apart. Actually, Rho Cas is in the process of doing just that. Three times in the last six decades, it has blasted shells of gas into space. The most recent expelled 20 times more material than is contained in all of the planets and moons of our solar system combined. The star could be building up to another eruption soon.\n\nCassiopeia has produced two supernovae in recent centuries. One of those, known today as Cassiopeia A, exploded about three centuries ago as seen from Earth. It blasted its outer layers into space at a few percent of the speed of light. This material continues to expand into space as a giant shell. It contains lots of oxygen and other elements that will disperse into the galaxy. These elements may someday be incorporated into new stars, planets, or even living organisms.\n\nIn addition to dead stars and stars that are about to die, Cassiopeia is also home to one of the largest collections of young stars in the galaxy. A few years ago, astronomers discovered a tight cluster of several very young, hot, massive stars there. The stars are similar to the brightest stars of the Orion Nebula, which is the largest stellar nursery in our region of the galaxy. Today, the stars in the Cassiopeia nebula are hidden inside a dense cloud of dust. But over the next hundred thousand years or so, the radiation and winds from these stars will eat through the dust, allowing future skywatchers to see the many other stars that have been born there.\n\n</string>
  <string name="cygnus_desc">The brightest stars of Cygnus form a cross, so the swan is also known as the Northern Cross. Find it soaring high overhead during late summer evenings.\n\nThe constellation\'s brightest star is Deneb — an Arabic word that means \"the tail.\" Deneb represents the tail of the swan but the top of the cross. The swan\'s outstretched wings form the horizontal bar of the cross, while the head of the swan, a double star called Albireo, is at the bottom of the cross.\n\nAlthough it lies about 1,500 light-years from Earth, Deneb shines brightly in our night sky because it\'s a white supergiant — a star that\'s much larger, hotter, and brighter than the Sun. Deneb is the northeastern point of a star pattern called the Summer Triangle.\n\nIf you use binoculars to scan the area between the two bright stars that define the swan\'s eastern wing, you\'ll see the remnant of a supernova — a faint, incomplete ring of light called the Cygnus Loop.\n\n</string>
  <string name="gemini_desc">Gemini is easy to find as it glides high overhead in mid-winter, above and to the left of Orion. Its two brightest stars, Castor and Pollux, represent the mythological twin brothers of Helen of Troy.\n\nMany cultures have seen two humans in this star pattern, which consists of two roughly parallel lines of stars capped by two of the brightest stars in the night sky. But the legend that endures is that of Castor and Pollux. Gemini\'s two brightest stars bear the names of the twins.\n\nAccording to the most common version of theirstory, the queen of Sparta gave birth to two sets of twins, with one boy and one girl in each pair. One set was fathered by her husband, the other by Zeus, king of the gods. The four children were raised together, and the two boys — one mortal, the other immortal — were inseparable. They had many adventures, and joined Jason and the other Argonauts in the search for the golden fleece.\n\nBut during a fight with some landowners, the mortal Castor was killed. Pollux was inconsolable, and eventually begged Zeus to allow him to die so he could join Castor. Moved by Pollux\'s love for his brother, Zeus agreed to keep them together for eternity. They spend half of their time in the underworld, the other half in the heavens, where they are represented by the stars of Gemini.\n\nPollux is the brighter of the twins. The orange-giant star is about 35 light-years from Earth. At least one planet orbits the star. It is at least three times as massive as Jupiter, and it orbits Pollux once every 1.6 years.\n\nCastor consists of six stars. This crowded system lies about 50 light-years from Earth. All six stars in the system really are related, because they were born from a single giant cloud of gas and dust, probably around 200 million years ago.\n\nTwo pairs of Castor\'s twins are more fraternal than identical. One star in each pair is a good bit bigger, brighter, and heavier than the Sun, while the other star in each pair is smaller, fainter, and less massive than the Sun. The stars in each of these pairs are so close together that they orbit each other in just a few days. At such close range, there\'s no way for telescopes to see them as individual stars. Instead, special instruments separate the \"fingerprints\" of the stars as they go around each other, providing details on each star.\n\nThe third set of Castor twins is identical. Each star is smaller, cooler, and less massive than the Sun, and much fainter. And while the other two sets of twins are relatively close to each other, these \"twins\" are so far away that it takes thousands of years to orbit the others.\n\nThe star cluster M35 stands near the feet of the twins. It is about 2,800 light-years away, and it contains a couple of thousand stars. Astronomers estimate that the cluster is about 150 million years old. That\'s  long enough for many of the cluster\'s original stars to have been pulled away by the gravity of the rest of the galaxy. But M35\'s remaining stars are bound together so strongly by their mutual gravitational pull that they\'re likely to stay together for a long time.\n\nM35\'s stars all started with roughly the same amounts of hydrogen, helium, and other elements. By studying how much of these elements the stars have today, astronomers learn a great deal about how stars evolve. The cluster\'s hottest, heaviest stars have already expired. Some may have blasted themselves to bits, while others cast their outer layers into space in a more gentle process, leaving behind their hot, dense cores.\n\nThe constellation is home to the Geminid meteor shower, which peaks in mid-December. If you trace their paths across the sky, the meteors all point back toward Gemini.</string>
  <string name="leo_desc">The zodiacal constellation Leo, the lion, is one of a handful of constellations that really does look like its namesake. It consists of two patterns of stars that the brain puts together to make a lion. A backward question mark represents the head and mane, and a triangle of stars to the lower left forms the lion\'s hindquarters and tail. Look for Leo high in the south in April and May.\n\nLeo\'s brightest star is blue-white Regulus, one of the brightest stars in the night sky. It is about 79 light-years away. Regulus rises almost due east, with the body of the lion following it into the sky over the next couple of hours. Once Regulus climbs into the sky, look to its left — toward the north — for the backwards question mark, known as the Sickle, that outlines his head and mane.\n\nAbout two hours later, look low in the east for Leo\'s tail — a white star named Denebola, which comes from an Arabic name that, appropriately enough, means \"tail of the lion.\"\n\nAt a distance of just 36 light-years, Denebola is a fairly close neighbor. Even so, the fact that we can see it at all means that Denebola is quite bright — more than 10 times brighter than the Sun. Denebola\'s brightness is a product of its mass. The star is about twice as heavy as the Sun, so it \"fuses\" the hydrogen in its core at a much faster rate. That makes the star\'s surface thousands of degrees hotter than the Sun\'s. The combination of high temperature and large size makes Denebola outshine the Sun and all but a few percent of all the stars in the Milky Way galaxy.\n\nDenebola is surrounded by a disk of dust grains. It may be supplied with fresh material by collisions between small planet-building bodies. So far, no one has seen any evidence of planets around the star, although they can\'t be ruled out, either. Astronomers continue to hunt for companions to this bright stellar neighbor.\n\nLeo also contains quite a few bright galaxies. Leading the list are three galaxies that together form the Leo Triplet: M65, M66, and NGC 3628.\n\nNGC 3628 is the most interesting of the three. Like our own Milky Way, it\'s a spiral — a pinwheel that spans at least a hundred thousand light-years. We see it edge-on, so it looks like a streak of light with lanes of dark dust running down the middle. Gravitational encounters with the other galaxies have triggered the birth of perhaps millions of new stars near the galaxy\'s center. They have pulled out a tail of gas that spans a quarter-million light-years. The tail contains enough gas to make half a billion stars as massive as the Sun. In fact, it has given birth to millions of stars in several large clumps.</string>
  <string name="libra_desc">Libra represents a balance scale. The name may come from the fact that the Sun passed across the face of the constellation at the time of the autumnal equinox in September, when day and night are of roughly equal length, so the heavens are \"balanced.\"\n\nLibra\'s brightest stars, however, are named for the next constellation over, Scorpius.\n\nThe stars are Zubenelgenubi and Zubeneschamali, which are Arabic names that mean the southern and northern claws, respectively. In ancient times, the stars represented the scorpion\'s claws. By thousands of years ago, however, the claws had been snipped off and assigned to Libra instead. The timing of the split is unclear, although it dates at least to the days of ancient Rome.\n\nZubenelgenubi actually consists of at least four stars, which are split into two close pairs. Three of the four are bigger and hotter than the Sun, while the fourth is smaller and cooler. All four appear to be about 200 million years old.\n\nLibra is also home to a star system that contains six planets or more, including one that is in an orbit where conditions are suitable for liquid water, which is a key ingredient for life. Artist\'s concept of Gliese 581\nAn artist\'s concept shows three of the planets known to orbit Gliese 581\n\nThe star, Gliese 581, is a red dwarf, which means it is much smaller, fainter, and cooler than the Sun. The lightest of the planets is only about twice the mass of Earth. It is so close to the star, though, that it\'s much too hot for water. The planet Gliese 581d, however is inside the star\'s habitable zone, which is the distance where conditions are just right for liquid water. That makes Gliese 581d one of the first \"water worlds\" yet discovered.</string>
  <string name="lyra_desc">It\'s easy to find Lyra, the harp, by first finding Vega — one of the brightest stars in Earth\'s night sky. Look for Vega high overhead in mid-summer. Lyra looks like a small, lopsided square, with Vega just beside one of the corners of the square.\n\nThe legend of Lyra tells the story of Orpheus, who was given a harp by the god Apollo. Orpheus\' music was sweeter than that of any other mortal man. It could soothe any savage, bring joy to the heart of the weary. It was even said that rivers changed course to stay near its beauty.\n\nOrpheus married the lovely maiden Eurydice. But after their wedding, as she walked with her bridesmaids, she was bitten by a snake and died.\n\nOrpheus was so stricken with grief that he journeyed to the underworld to win her return. His music not only gained him entry to Hades, it caused Pluto, the god of the underworld, to soften his heart and grant Orpheus\' wish. But there was one condition: Eurydice would follow Orpheus, who could not look back until both had gained the upper world. Orpheus followed his instructions — until he reached the surface. Before Eurydice could take the final steps into the light, he turned to gaze upon her. She vanished, with only one word to her love: Farewell.\n\nCrazed with grief, Orpheus wandered the hills of Greece until he was murdered. The Muses buried him, and Apollo placed his magical harp in the sky — as Lyra.\n\nLyra\'s leading light, Vega, is only about 25 light-years away, making it one of our closest neighbors. It shines pure white, which tells us that its surface is thousands of degrees hotter than the surface of the Sun.\n\nModels of how stars age indicate that, like the Sun, Vega is about halfway through its \"normal\" lifetime — the time when it fuses the hydrogen atoms in its core to make helium. But stellar lifetimes aren\'t all the same. Vega is probably around one-tenth the age of the Sun, so it has only a few hundred million years to go, versus billions of years for the Sun.\n\nThe difference is the mass of the two stars. Vega is more than twice as heavy as the Sun, so it burns through its hydrogen much faster than the Sun does. So Vega will finish its hydrogen, puff up to become a red giant, blow its outer layers off into space, and fade into obscurity as a white dwarf — all while the Sun continues to shine much as it does today.\n\nThe constellation\'s second-brightest star, Beta Lyrae, stands a bit to the south of Vega.\n\nBeta Lyrae is a binary, so it consists of two stars locked in a mutual orbit around each other. Both stars are larger, hotter, and brighter than the Sun. One star is blue, and the other is white. The stars are so close together that each star\'s gravity has distorted the other, making them look like eggs.\n\nThe two stars are so close together that they orbit each other once every 13 days. And during every orbit, one star passes in front of the other as seen from Earth, blocking its light. You can even see these eclipses with just your eyes. Just compare Beta Lyrae\'s brightness to that of Gamma Lyrae, the star that\'s next to it. Normally, they\'re the same brightness. But during an eclipse, Beta looks fainter, because you are seeing the light of only one star instead of two.\n\nLyra hosts the \"radiant\" for the Lyrid meteor shower, which peaks each April. That means that if you trace their paths back across the sky, the meteors all appears to \"rain\" into Earth\'s atmosphere from the direction of Lyra.</string>
  <string name="orion_desc">Orion is one of the most beautiful of all constellations, and one of the easiest to find. It looks like a large rectangle high in winter\'s south-southeastern sky.\n\nTwo of the brightest stars in the evening sky lie at opposite corners of the rectangle: bright orange-red Betelgeuse at the northeastern corner and even brighter Rigel at the southwest.\n\nBetelgeuse is at least 300 times the Sun\'s diameter, and perhaps much more. It puts out about 100,000 times more energy than the Sun does. And when it dies, it will create a fireball that will briefly outshine billions of normal stars.\n\nBetelgeuse is a red supergiant — the largest class of stars. It’s probably close to 20 times as massive as the Sun. The gravity of such a star squeezes its core tightly, heating it to billions of degrees. Such a stellar blast furnace consumes its original hydrogen fuel in a hurry, “fusing” the atoms together to make helium and producing incredible amounts of energy in the process. It then fuses the helium to make heavier elements — carbon and oxygen at first, and eventually all the way up to iron. When that happens, the star no longer produces energy in the core. Without the reactions in its core to push outward, gravity quickly causes the core to collapse, forming a neutron star. A massive explosion rips through the star’s outer layers, blasting them into space at a few percent of the speed of light — a titanic blast known as a supernova. We can’t be sure when that will happen to Betelgeuse, but it’s probably soon on the astronomical time scale: just about anytime in the next hundred thousand years.\n\nRigel is a blue supergiant. Like Betelgeuse, it is much bigger and heavier than the Sun. It\'s surface is thousands of degrees hotter, however, so it shines blue-white. That high temperature means that Rigel also pumps out a lot of ultraviolet energy, which produces sunburn and other problems. When you add up the ultraviolet, visible light, and other wavelengths, Rigel shines tens of thousands of times brighter than the Sun. In fact, depending on Rigel\'s exact distance, it could be up to 100,000  times brighter than the Sun.\n\nWith so much energy streaming its way, a planet would need to be billions of miles away from Rigel to be a safe abode for life, and it would need a thick ozone layer to screen out the ultraviolet. Even then, such a planet wouldn\'t be a good long-term home. In a few million years, Rigel, too, is likely to blast itself to bits as a supernova. The energy and shock wave would make quick work of life on any world around it.\n\nNear the center of Orion\'s prominent rectangle, look for a short diagonal line of three stars that forms Orion\'s Belt. And extending south from the belt, you\'ll see another, fainter line of stars that forms Orion\'s Sword.\n\nOne of the objects in the sword isn\'t a star at all. It\'s M42, the Orion Nebula, which is a cloud of gas and dust that\'s like a giant fluorescent bulb.\n\nM42 is part of a giant complex of clouds of interstellar gas and dust. Pockets of this material are collapsing to give birth to new stars. Hubble Space Telescope images reveal about 3,000 stars in the Orion Nebula alone, some of which could be as little as 10,000 years old.\n\nThe visible nebula is a bubble of turbulent gas that is energized by the Trapezium, a cluster of hot, bright stars at its center. Ultraviolet energy from the stars strips electrons from atoms in the nebula. When the electrons link up with new atoms, the atoms emit light.\n\nThe process of starbirth continues today, with several hundred dense blobs of gas and dust collapsing to make new stars. In addition, planetary systems appear to be taking shape around many of the newborn stars. Not all of them will survive the birth process, though, because radiation from the cluster\'s hot young stars is eroding the planet-making materials around many of the stars.</string>
  <string name="pegasus_desc">Pegasus is a large pattern of stars marked by a great square — four bright stars that form the body of the winged horse.\n\nPegasus is a character from Mediterranean mythology, although he\'s best known for a couple of myths that he wasn\'t part of — those of Perseus and Hercules.\n\nIn classical Greek mythology, Perseus killed the snake-headed Medusa to save the princess Andromeda from a nasty sea monster. A few drops of Medusa\'s blood fell into the sea. When it mixed with the foam, it gave birth to Pegasus, who later played a part in the story of another hero, Bellerophon. In modern times, though, Pegasus has become a more integral part of the Perseus story. In recent tellings, when Perseus shows up to save Andromeda, he is riding Pegasus. And the tale of the flying horse became even more convoluted with Disney\'s animated version of Hercules, in which Herc and Pegasus are pals.\n\nThe brightest star in the Great Square, Alpheratz, isn\'t in the constellation Pegasus. It\'s in Andromeda, which is just northeast of Pegasus. It is part of the ancient sky picture that we know as Pegasus. But when astronomers drew the official boundaries for the constellations, this star was placed just across the line in Andromeda.\n\nThe brightest star in the constellation is Markab, which means \"the saddle.\" It\'s at the southwestern corner of the Great Square.\n\nAt another corner is Beta Pegasi. \"Beta\" means it should be the second-brightest star in Pegasus, and sometimes it is. The star pulses in and out like a beating heart. When it pulses out, its surface cools, so it gets fainter. When it squeezes back in it gets hotter, so it glows brighter, making it Pegasus\'s brightest star.\n\nAnother star in Pegasus, II Pegasi, produced a monster flare a few years ago — a powerful explosion on its surface that generated a torrent of energy and charged particles. The flare was 100 million times more powerful than a typical flare on the Sun. If Earth orbited II Pegasi, such a monster would obliterate the ozone layer and alter the climate, and probably kill much of the planet\'s life. The star\'s magnetic field may be energized by a nearby companion star, which causes II Pegasi to spin on its axis once every seven days (versus about 29 days for the Sun). This fast rotation may keep the star\'s internal layers in high-speed motion, generating a powerful magnetic field that produces flares and other storms.</string>
  <string name="perseus_desc">Perseus, the hero, arcs high overhead in fall and early winter. Many of its stars are immersed in the faint glow of our galaxy, the Milky Way. In fact, if you look at Perseus under dark skies, you may be able to see three of the spiral arms that enfold the Milky Way.\n\nIn classical Greek mythology, Perseus beheaded the snake-headed Medusa to save the princess Andromeda from a nasty sea monster. A few drops of Medusa\'s blood fell into the sea, mixed with the foam, and gave birth to Pegasus, the flying horse, who later played a part in the story of another hero, Bellerophon.\n\nThe constellation\'s brightest star, Alpha Persei, is a bit brighter than the North Star. It is moving through space with a large group of stars, known collectively as the Alpha Persei cluster. The cluster is only about 50 million years old, which is just one percent of the age of the Sun and Earth.\n\nOne of the brightest and most interesting stars in Perseus is Algol. The name Algol means \"demon star.\" Ancient skywatchers thought it was cursed because its brightness changes. That\'s because Algol, which is about 75 light-years from Earth, is the most famous eclipsing binary star. Today, astronomers know that Algol is two separate stars. About once every three days, the fainter member of the pair passes in front of the brighter one, and Algol grows fainter.\n\nA faint star cluster in Perseus, called M34 is visible with binoculars.\n\nPerseus is also the \"radiant\" point of the Perseid meteor shower, which is visible every August. Although the meteors can streak across any part of the sky, if you trace their paths backwards they all appear to originate in Perseus. The shower is spawned by Comet Swift-Tuttle. As it orbits the Sun, this big \"dirty snowball\" sheds tiny grains of rock and dust. Over time, the particles spread out along the comet\'s orbital path. Earth flies through this path every August, sweeping up some of the dust grains. They plunge into our atmosphere at more than 100,000 miles per hour, vaporizing as the streaks of light known as meteors.</string>
  <string name="pisces_desc">In the lore of the sky, spring is associated with the constellation Aries, the ram. Yet at the moment of the vernal equinox, which marks the beginning of spring in the northern hemisphere, the Sun actually stands within the borders of the next constellation over — Pisces, the fishes.\n\nSeveral thousand years ago, when the zodiac was first drawn, the Sun stood inside Aries at the time of the equinox. And today, the March equinox is still known as the \"first point of Aries.\" Yet the Sun has moved from Aries into Pisces because of an effect known as precession. It is a wobble in Earth\'s rotation caused by the gravitational pull of the Sun and Moon. As a result of this wobble, the point of the equinox moves all the way around the sky. That means that as the centuries roll by, the Sun appears against different stars at the equinox.\n\nPisces, which is best viewed during autumn and winter evenings, is one of the constellations of the zodiac. Despite this claim to fame, though, Pisces is tough to see. Even its brightest stars are no match for the light pollution from many cities and suburbs.\n\nPisces is one member of the \"celestial sea,\" a group of constellations that are all related to water. These constellations probably were associated with water because the Sun passed across them during the rainy season in the ancient Middle East.\n\nSeveral thousand years ago, when the zodiac was first drawn, the Sun stood inside Aries at the time of the equinox. And today, the March equinox is still known as the \n\nAlthough none of its stars is particularly impressive, Pisces is home to several beautiful galaxies. One of the most prominent is M74, a spiral galaxy that we view almost exactly face on. It\'s just 24 million light-years away.\n\nM74 resembles a slightly smaller version of the Milky Way, so it looks like a glowing cosmic pinwheel. Its spiral arms contain clouds of gas and dust that create new stars. The brightest and hottest of these new stars are blue, giving the spiral arms a blue tint. The hottest newborn stars emit radiation that strips the electrons from hydrogen atoms in these clouds. As the electrons rejoin the atoms, they emit a red glow, so the clouds of hydrogen look like red or pink dots.</string>
  <string name="sagittarius_desc">Sagittarius, the archer, slides low across the southern sky of summer. Sagittarius is a centaur — a mythological half-man, half-horse — who has drawn his bow. His arrow is pointing at Antares, the bright red heart of Scorpius, the scorpion. The archer is avenging Orion, who was slain by the scorpion\'s sting.\n\nThe constellation originated in Sumeria, then was picked up by the Greeks. But they appear to have missed something in the translation. The original story may have described a satyr, which was part man and part goat. One of these creatures was credited with inventing archery, which was why he was depicted in the sky with a bow and arrow. The Greeks kept the bow and arrow, but changed the creature.\n\nTo most modern eyes, though, the brightest stars of Sagittarius appear to outline not a mythological creature but a teapot. Steam pours from the spout — the hazy starclouds of the Milky Way.\n\nThe center of the Milky Way galaxy is immersed in that steam, about 27,000 light-years away. Although the galaxy\'s core is packed with stars, interstellar dust between the core and Earth absorbs most of its light, rendering it invisible except to instruments that study wavelengths of light that penetrate the dust.\n\nOne part of the classical picture that is fairly easy to see is the bow. The star that represents the top of the bow is at the top of the teapot, with the bottom of the bow at the bottom right of the teapot. A star that is about halfway between them represents the middle of the bow. The stars are named Kaus Borealis, Kaus Media, and Kaus Australis, which is a combination of Arabic and Latin that means the northern, middle, and southern bow.\n\nKaus Australis — the southern end of the bow — is the brightest star in the constellation. It is a stellar giant — a star that has puffed up as it nears the end of its life. It\'s many times larger than the Sun, and almost 400 times brighter. That makes it quite easy to see even though it\'s about 145 light-years away. The bow\'s other stars are giants, too. The one in the middle is actually the most impressive of the lot — it\'s bigger and brighter than the others, but farther away.\n\nThe steam above the spout includes two nebulae that are giving birth to new star clusters: M8 (the Lagoon Nebula) and M20 (the Trifid Nebula).\n\nThe Lagoon has given birth to scores of stars, with more taking shape even now. Through binoculars or a small telescope, it looks like a hazy oval of light. Photographs show a reddish-pink glow, which is the color of hydrogen atoms being zapped by the radiation of young stars.\n\nLanes of dark dust across the face of M20 give it a three-part appearance. A young star at the center of the nebula, which lights up much of the material around it, is triggering the formation of more than a hundred other stars.\n\nSagittarius also contains several globular clusters, which are tightly packed collections of hundreds of thousands of stars.</string>
  <string name="scorpius_desc">Three bright stars form the \"head\" of Scorpius, the celestial scorpion, while its tail curves away below it in the southern sky of summer.\n\nThe brightest star in Scorpius is Antares, which is in the middle of the scorpion\'s curving body. This brilliant red star is one of the behemoths of our stellar neighborhood. If you placed it at the center of our own solar system, it would swallow Mercury, Venus, Earth, and Mars, and almost reach Jupiter.\n\nAntares is at least 15 times as massive as the Sun. The pressure in the centers of such stars makes them extremely hot. The heat allows chemical elements to fuse together to make heavier ones. So by the end of its life, Antares will have built up an iron core surrounded by layers of oxygen, carbon, silicon, and other elements. And at the end of its life, Antares will explode as a supernova. The extreme heat of the blast will produce elements that are even heavier than iron — elements like lead, uranium, and gold.\n\nThe explosion will hurl these elements outward at a few percent of the speed of light. Eventually, some of the debris may ram into clouds of cold gas and dust, squeezing them and causing them to collapse and give birth to new stars and planets. These newborn objects will be seeded with the elements created by the supernova.\n\nBecause Scorpius lies along the path of the Milky Way, it is speckled with bright star clusters and nebulae, including the clusters M6 and M7, which are above the two stars that mark the scorpion\'s stinger.\n\nM7 is the brighter of the two. It is almost 1,000 light-years away, and its several hundred stars all are about 200 million to 300 million years old. Several of its stars are nearing the ends of their lives, so they have puffed up to gigantic proportions, helping M7 stand out.\n\nM6 is farther than M7, so it doesn’t look as big or bright, so you need dark skies to see it without optical aid. Through binoculars or a telescope, the cluster’s colorful stars form a pattern that resembles the outline of a butterfly.</string>
  <string name="taurus_desc">Taurus, the bull, is marked by a V-shaped pattern of stars that outlines the bull\'s face. Bright red Aldebaran, the \"eye\" of the bull, stands at one point of the V. This pattern is part of a cluster of stars called the Hyades — the second-closest star cluster to Earth. It consists of several hundred stars that lie about 130 light-years away.\n\nAldebaran outshines all the other stars that outline the bull\'s face. But Aldebaran isn\'t a member of the Hyades cluster — it just lies in the same direction. It\'s about 70 light-years away, half as far as the stars of the Hyades. Aldebaran is a red-giant — an old, bloated star that\'s used up most of its nuclear fuel. It\'s much larger and much brighter than our own middle-aged Sun.</string>
  <string name="ursa_major_desc">Ursa Major — the great bear — is always above the horizon in the northern latitudes, but the best time to see it is in the spring when its high above the northeastern horizon. Ursa Major is best known as the home of the Big Dipper.\n\nOf all the star patterns in the sky, the Big Dipper is the most universally recognized. The dipper\'s seven bright stars form a portion of the great bear. It\'s hard to see the rest of the bear, especially from light-polluted cities.\n\nAfter you locate the dipper, look at the two stars that mark the outer edge of its bowl. Now connect these two stars, then extend the line above the dipper\'s bowl. Polaris, the north star, lies along this line, about five times the distance between the two pointers. No matter where the Big Dipper is in our sky, those two stars always point to Polaris.</string>
  <string name="virgo_desc">Virgo is the second-largest constellation — so big that it takes about four hours for the whole thing to clear the eastern horizon. To the unaided eye, though, that huge area is basically a void, because only one bright star resides within its borders.\n\nIn mythology, Virgo was associated with the harvest. It represented a harvest goddess or the daughter of a goddess. The constellation\'s brightest star, Spica, was a stalk of wheat held in her hand. Virgo was associated with the harvest because the Sun passed across the constellation during late summer or early autumn, when farmers were reaping the crops they had planted months earlier.\n\nVirgo is known as a spring constellation because, although you can see some or all of its stars on most nights of the year, the stars put on their best display in the evening sky during spring.\n\nAlthough blue-white Spica is Virgo\'s only bright star, it is the 16th-brightest star in the night sky. It actually consists of two stars, both of which are much hotter, brighter, and heavier than the Sun. But they are separated by only about 10 million miles, so from Spica\'s distance of 260 light-years, it is impossible to see them as individual stars.\n\nBecause the stars are big, heavy, and close together, they exert such a strong gravitational tug on each other that each star causes the other to bulge outward. Seen in profile, the system would look like two eggs with the narrow ends pointed at each other.\n\nIn the next few million years, the heavier star will near the end of its “normal” lifetime, so it will puff up to many times its current size. As it swells, some of its gas will begin to dump onto the surface of the other star. And as it gets even bigger, its outer layers will engulf its partner, pulling the two stellar cores closer together. No one knows exactly how the scenario will play out after that. The stars may merge to form a single star, or the larger star may explode before that can happen, blasting itself to bits and perhaps sending its companion careening through the galaxy like a stellar bullet.\n\nThe second-brightest star in Virgo, Gamma Virginis, is also a binary system. Unlike Spica, its stars are so far apart that binoculars easily reveal them as individual stars. They are about 40 light-years from Earth. The stars are both white, which means their surfaces are a little hotter than the surface of the Sun. They\'re both brighter than the Sun, too.\n\nGamma Virginis has been known by several other names over the centuries. One of the most enduring is Porrima, for the goddess of prophecy. In ancient Babylon, it was called Star of the Hero, and in China, it was the High Minister of State.\n\nWhile Spica is the most prominent object in Virgo, the most interesting may be the Virgo Cluster — a collection of several thousand galaxies. It is centered about 60 million light-years away.\n\nThe cluster forms the largest structure in our region of the universe. The galaxies are bound to each other by their gravity, so they move through space together. The cluster exerts a strong tug on our own galaxy, the Milky Way, and the small band of galaxies that it\'s bound to, the Local Group. The Local Group is being pulled toward the Virgo Cluster, and eventually may join it.\n\nThe largest member of the cluster is M87, which spans one million light-years and contains one trillion stars or more. It\'s a type of galaxy known as a giant elliptical. It looks like a fat, fuzzy football. Its core is inhabited by one of the largest black holes yet discovered, a monster about 6.6 billion times the mass of the Sun.\n\nAt the other end of the distance scale, Virgo also is home to two of the closest star systems. But the stars are so puny that they are not visible to the unaided eye. One system, Ross 128, is less than 11 light-years away; only 10 known star systems are closer. The other, which a pair of stars known as Wolf 424, is just four light-years farther. Both stars are classified as red dwarfs. They are much less massive than the Sun, so they\'re only about one ten-thousandth as bright. If any of these stars took the Sun\'s place, daytime on Earth would be only a few times brighter than a night with a full Moon, and Earth would be an iceball, with no chance for life as we know it.</string>

  <string name="content_attribution">\n\n\n\nUsed by permission of The University of Texas McDonald Observatory.</string>

  <string name="enable_shortcut">Enable Shortcut</string>
  <string name="disable_shortcut">Disable Shortcut</string>
  <string name="shortcut_enabled">Shortcut Enabled</string>
  <string name="shortcut_disabled">Shortcut Disabled</string>
  <string name="request_pin_shortcut">Request Pin Shortcut</string>
</resources>